Guide to the Paul Bowen Johnson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul Bowen Johnson papers
1918-1937
MS 914
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Letters and papers relating to the work of Paul Bowen Johnson, who was a captain in the Medical Corps, as Morale Officer for the Port of Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia, during World War I. Also in the papers is a history of the Morale Department and his own log of work between 1918-1919.
Johnson, Paul Bowen, 1878-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Bowen Johnson, 1947.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of letters and papers, 1918-1919, relating to the work of Paul Bowen Johnson, captain in the Medical Corps, as Morale Officer for the Port of Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia, during World War I.
Included are several letters to and from Army officers and civilians concerning the activities of the Morale Department, as well as orders, memoranda, and official papers from the War Department, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed matter, all relating to the Port of Embarkation and the Morale Department. Also among the papers are a typed history of the Morale Department which explains its work maintaining the health and well-being of soldiers throughout their service in the Army, written by Johnson, and his own log of his work as Morale Officer between November 13, 1918, and August 1, 1919. The volume also contains minutes of meetings with the Morale Department and with civilian welfare groups, copies of orders, and related matter.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Bowen Alden Johnson was born in Washington, D.C., on March 23, 1878. He was educated at Central High School and Yale College, where he graduated with the class of 1901. After graduation, he studied medicine at Georgetown University, where he received the degree of M.D. in 1905. During World War I, he was a captain in the Medical Corps. In 1921, he was appointed full professor at the Schools of Medicine and Dentistry at Georgetown. Johnson was secretary of the Social Hygiene Association of the District of Columbia; a member of various medical associations; and he belonged to the American Legion, the Society of Mayflower Descendants, the Mt. Pleasant Citizens' Association, etc. He lived the rest of his life in Washington, D.C., where he died on January 16, 1954.
World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; Diaries; Soldiers; Johnson, Paul Bowen, 1878-1954
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Orders and memoranda, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Forms for discharge from the Army, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous military papers, 1918-1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "History of the Morale Department. Port of Embarkation, Newport News, Virginia", 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Log Notes of Captain Paul B. Johnson", 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed matter, 1919, [1931?, 1937?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Registration certificates, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Identification pass, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)